<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wu-kiot.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://wu-kiot.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-09T02:07:40+00:00</updated><id>https://wu-kiot.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">NLP and AI Team at WU, KIOT</title><link href="https://wu-kiot.github.io/blog/2024/NLP-AI-Team-WU-KIoT/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NLP and AI Team at WU, KIOT"/><published>2024-12-24T08:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-24T08:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wu-kiot.github.io/blog/2024/NLP-AI-Team-WU-KIoT</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wu-kiot.github.io/blog/2024/NLP-AI-Team-WU-KIoT/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="advancing-ethiopian-languages-through-ai-the-nlp-and-data-science-team-at-kiot">Advancing Ethiopian Languages Through AI: The NLP and Data Science Team at KIoT</h1> <p>Welcome to our blog, where we chronicle the journey of establishing the NLP and Data Science team at the Kombolcha Institute of Technology (KIoT) at Wollo University. This groundbreaking initiative, inspired by <a href="https://seyyaw.github.io/">Dr. Seid Muhie Yimam</a> from the University of Hamburg and supported by the <a href="https://www.iom.int/">International Organization for Migration (IOM)</a>, was launched during Dr. Seid’s visit to our university. In this post, we delve into the team’s formation, the innovative projects underway, and our collaborations aimed at addressing local challenges through cutting-edge technology.</p> <h2 id="our-mission">Our Mission</h2> <p>We are a team of passionate researchers, instructors, and collaborators committed to adapting global AI and data science advancements to Ethiopian languages and task-specific challenges across industries. Focusing on Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Data Science, our work aims to enhance accessibility, drive innovation, and empower communities through localized technological solutions.</p> <h2 id="the-nlp-and-data-science-team-at-kiot">The NLP and Data Science Team at KIoT</h2> <ul> <li>Established: December 2024</li> <li>Location: Kombolcha Institute of Technology (KIoT), Wollo University</li> <li>Core Focus Areas: Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Data Science</li> </ul> <p>Drawing expertise from the Faculty of Informatics, our team is dedicated to pioneering solutions tailored to Ethiopia’s linguistic and industrial needs. We collaborate with institutions such as Bahir Dar University and EthioNLP to expand our reach and capabilities.</p> <h2 id="natural-language-processing-nlp">Natural Language Processing (NLP)</h2> <p>The NLP sub-team focuses on advancing technology that can process and understand Ethiopian languages effectively. Key projects include:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Basic Preprocessing for Local Languages: Developing robust pipelines for text normalization, tokenization, and segmentation to address the unique linguistic challenges of Ethiopian languages.</p> </li> <li> <p>Fine-Tuning Large Language Models (LLMs): Adapting state-of-the-art LLMs to Ethiopian languages, ensuring they capture linguistic nuances and cultural contexts. This work supports tasks like text summarization, translation, and sentiment analysis.</p> </li> <li> <p>Speech Recognition: Collaborating with Bahir Dar University to fine-tune models such as Whisper for Ethiopian dialects, enhancing audio transcription accuracy and accessibility.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="data-science">Data Science</h2> <p>Our Data Science sub-team leverages AI and data science methodologies to address pressing challenges in various sectors:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Healthcare: Using predictive modeling to enhance diagnostics and patient care, improving health outcomes and service accessibility.</p> </li> <li> <p>Agriculture: Developing data-driven solutions for crop yield prediction, soil analysis, and smart farming techniques to boost productivity and sustainability.</p> </li> <li> <p>Smart City Solutions: Implementing urban planning tools, traffic management systems, and environmental monitoring to foster efficient and sustainable cities.</p> </li> <li> <p>Finance: Designing predictive algorithms for fraud detection, credit risk analysis, and financial inclusivity.</p> </li> <li> <p>Manufacturing and Industries: Optimizing production processes and supply chains through AI-powered insights.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="meet-the-team">Meet the Team</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://seyyaw.github.io/">Dr. Seid Muhie Yimam</a> (University of Hamburg)</li> <li>Tadesse Destaw</li> <li>Dawit Ketema (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Bedru Yimam (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Yohannes Ayana (Bahir Dar University)</li> <li>Hassen Ebrahim (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Mohammed Oumer (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Kassahun Asbo (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Mulugeta Linger (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Endalkachew Hiwot (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Tadesse Amare (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Kebadu [Father’s Name] (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Shambel Dessale</li> <li>Alemu Belay (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> <li>Esmael Ahmed (Wollo University, KIoT)</li> </ul> <h2 id="key-initiatives">Key Initiatives</h2> <p>The Two-Week Mission by Dr. Seid Muhie Yimam</p> <p>Dr. Seid’s visit catalyzed the creation of the NLP and Data Science team. His guidance continues to shape our projects and methodologies.</p> <ul> <li> <p>NLP projects initiated for sub-teams as detailed in the “Ongoing Projects” section.</p> </li> <li> <p>Seminars:</p> <ul> <li>Open Sourcing - Open code, open data, open opportunity</li> <li>Big Data and AI: Enhancing Prognostic and Diagnostic Capabilities</li> <li>Academic and Grant Writing</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Open Source Philosophy</p> <p>Dr. Seid’s presentation and discussion at the seminar gave us insight into open sourcing, and we believe in the power of open access. Our projects emphasize open code, open data, and open opportunities to foster collaboration and innovation. Explore <a href="https://github.com/wu-kiot">our GitHub organization</a> and <a href="https://huggingface.co/wu-kiot">Hugging Face</a> hub for resources and cooperation.</p> <h2 id="ongoing-projects">Ongoing Projects</h2> <ul> <li> <p>LLM for News Generation: Fine-tuning language models to generate accurate and contextually rich news articles.</p> </li> <li> <p>LLM for Poem Generation: Exploring creative applications of AI in Ethiopian literature and poetry.</p> </li> <li> <p>Whisper Fine-Tuning: Improving speech recognition models for Ethiopian dialects.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2> <p>We envision a future where AI and data science are seamlessly integrated into Ethiopian industries, enabling progress and inclusivity. By addressing local challenges with global solutions, we aim to transform Ethiopia’s technological landscape. Join us on this journey as we continue to push the boundaries of what’s possible with NLP and Data Science in Ethiopia. Stay tuned for updates, insights, and opportunities to collaborate!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="blog"/><category term="NLP"/><category term="AI"/><category term="Ethiopia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Advancing Ethiopian Languages Through AI at Kombolcha Institute of Technology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">16ኛው የወሎ ዩኒቨርሲቲ የተማሪዎች ምረቃ – Wollo University</title><link href="https://wu-kiot.github.io/blog/2024/16-wollo-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="16ኛው የወሎ ዩኒቨርሲቲ የተማሪዎች ምረቃ – Wollo University"/><published>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wu-kiot.github.io/blog/2024/16------wollo-university</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wu-kiot.github.io/blog/2024/16-wollo-university/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>